hello this is dr eric bricker and thank
you for watching a healthcare z today's
topic is
cancer is variable by its severity
and by its cost so if you work in
healthcare administration or you work in
health insurance or you're working on
employee benefits or hr and you're
essentially a non-clinical person but
you work with
with health care it's super important
for you to understand cancer right
because so from a
disease standpoint we've always talked
about the large three disease
classifications
that drive so the highest degree of
healthcare costs being musculoskeletal
cardiovascular
and cancer and here on a healthcare see
we don't have we don't talk a lot
about cancer but there's some basic
cancer
terminology that you need to understand
in order frankly to just do your job
better okay
so first of all what you know at a very
basic we understand what is cancer right
it is
uncontrolled oftentimes malfunctioning
cell growth so it's uncontrolled so good
so the cells are growing
and those cells that are growing
uncontrollably in a way that they
shouldn't be growing
those cells also don't function the
right way and that's why it's a
devastating disease
that can obviously lead to death okay
now there's different ways to classify
cancers okay and you hear these terms
thrown around so i'm going to explain
them
first of all is the cancer grade which
is what it looks like
under the microscope to the pathologist
and
there are two grades there's high grade
which means that the cells are
poorly differentiated which means that
the cells look
really abnormal okay so high grade is
bad
and then there is low grade which means
that the cells are
highly differentiated and by
differentiated meaning
they look like the cells they're
supposed to look like they're supposed
to look like
a skin cell they're supposed to look
like a colon cell so
low grade is better
all right now there's also the
stage and the stage is broken down into
what is referred to as the tnm
system and t stands for tumor
n stands for nodes as in lymph nodes
and m is for metastasis and it has to do
with
how big the cancer has become locally
that's the tumor and if it has spread to
the lymph nodes and how many lymph nodes
it's spread to
and then m if it has metastasized or
spread
to other organs in the body so
oftentimes let's say
colon cancer will metastasize to either
the liver or the lungs it also can go to
the lymph nodes that are
in the abdominal cavity or it can be
just a localized
tumor in one specific area of the colon
now that's fine but you might say hey dr
bricker that's fine
but like when i hear about cancer i hear
about stage four cancer and stage one
cancer
so where do those numbers come from so
what they do by each individual cancer
breast cancer colon cancer lung cancer
is they take the and by the way there's
t one two three and four depending on
how big the tumor is there's nodes
one two three and four and there's
metastasis one two
three depending on how severe the tumor
is how many nodes it's gone to
and how many organ systems it's
metastasized to
so by cancer they then roll
those tnm scores up into
stage one or stage two or stage three
or stage four and typically stage one is
like just a tumor
nodes are negative no metastasis stage
two is like a larger tumor
and no nodes and no metastasis stage
three is oftentimes
a really large tumor yes it's spread to
the nodes but there's no metastasis
and then stage four is there's a tumor
there's nodes and there's metastasis
it varies by cancer type but that's how
you translate
the tumor the nodes and the metastasis
into that one through
four stage that you hear about so how do
you put the grade in the stage together
the worst type of cancer that you could
possibly have
is a high grade right because it's
poorly differentiated
the cells are like really cancerous and
it's metastatic and so what cancer
oftentimes falls into that category is
ovarian cancer
oftentimes it will grow inside the
abdominal cavity
and become and it's very high grade and
it's already spread to places like the
liver or even the brain
and uh and that's why ovarian cancer is
so lethal
uh and then sort of your best case
scenario for cancer would be a very low
grade
cancer in other words it's highly
differentiated it looks a lot like
normal cells it's only a little
different
and it has a very um
and it's only the tumor so like it would
be only like stage
one okay and that would be a like a
basal
basal cell uh carcinoma of the skin
right so basal cell carcinoma it's like
barely cancer like a lot of
it's like a little like wimpy cancer
okay
now another term that you'll hear about
is
in situ and in situ means
that the cancer cells are on a
microscopic level
very highly localized within the tissue
so not only has it not formed a tumor
that you can see or that you can feel
but also at the microscopic level
it has stayed very contained it hasn't
broken through something called the
lamina propria
so it's sort of boxed in if you will
okay so
that's important because breast the most
common type of breast cancer is what's
referred to as dcis
ductal carcinoma in situ so there's two
big types of breast cancer there's
dr carcinona ductal carcinoma and
lobular carcinoma okay and then
ductal is more common than lobular and
the most common type of ductile
is this ductal carcinoma in situ so it's
the ducts
uh used for lactation and milk
production
that actually become cancerous in the
breast and
20 of all breast cancers are dcis
which means they're very microscopically
localized to just the duct and that's a
good thing
okay now what that means is is that
the cancer if it's dcis dr carcinoma
inside tube
that means the treatment is just a
typically a surgical
lumpectomy where they only need to
remove a portion of the breast
surgically
and then in certain situations then the
the
woman needs to undergo radiation and in
some situations you don't even need to
go on a radiation and the great news is
is that if it's stuck to carcinoma
in situ then there's no need for
chemotherapy no need for the nausea or
the weight loss or the hair
falling out or the fatigue or the anemia
okay
so for not all cancers have to get chemo
right if you cut out a basal cell
carcinoma there's no you don't get chemo
at all if you have dcis breast cancer
you don't
get chemo okay so yeah you might take
tamoxifen or one of those pills but
that's hormone therapy that's that's
different than actual like iv
chemo if you have like stage you know
one two three or four breast cancer
which is separate from dcis then you
might actually need the chemo
which is something like uh adriamycin
cyclophosphamide
paclitaxel as well okay next you often
hear these different
sort of words associated with like the
naming of
cancer and we're going to go through
those names right so the first one
is carcinoma right so we talked about
ductal carcinoma in situ
we talked about basal cell carcinoma
okay so carcinomas are
solid tumors so tumors of your solid
organs of your body
that arise from the arise from the
epithelial cells and the epithelial
cells are the
lining or the covering of an organ or of
a duct
okay so next we have sarcomas
and sarcomas are cancers of the bone or
the muscle
or the fat in other words these are the
connective tissues
now sarcomas tend to not metastasize
they tend to just
grow more locally but they can still be
lethal
i had a friend of mine from college who
died of a sarcoma at the age of
35 so they can still be very serious
okay next up we have leukemia which is
referred to as like a liquid tumor so
this is a tumor of your
bone marrow so the tumor manifests
itself as your blood being thrown all
out of whack either because your white
blood cell count is super high and your
red blood cell count is super low
or sometimes your white blood cell count
and your red blood cell count are super
low so there's a
but those are liquid tumors okay not
solid tumors
and then there's lymphomas which is a
cancer of the lymph nodes or
also the spleen which is part of your
immune system
as well oftentimes that's where you hear
like hodgkin's and nod hodkins
lymphomas right there's also some mixed
tumors as well but these are the major
classifications when you hear those
words
thrown around okay now why is this
important okay there's a number of
reasons why you would practically use
this
when you are looking at claims data you
might see that some cancers
are very large claims and other cancers
are not let me give you some example
a basal cell uh carcinoma you're only
going to have the dermatologist remove
it like in the office maybe that's a
couple hundred bucks 250 bucks to remove
it
and then you're gonna have the
pathologist examine it under the
microscope to make sure that it's basal
cell carcinoma not something else
all told might cost 400
okay so very low cost likewise
if a person has certain types of
leukemia it may require a bone marrow
transplant and a bone marrow transplant
costs
over a million dollars so there is a so
so health care costs are a function of
the cost per unit times the number of
units well in some cases
the cost per unit and the number of
units is very low
and in other situations the cost per
unit and the number of units because the
bone marrow transplant
it's a it's got a whole bunch of
different steps it's got a long
hospitalization it's got a whole bunch
of follow-up afterwards
so you have a very high cost per unit
and you have a large number of
units okay so cancer is
highly heterogeneous in terms of its
impact on your employees and
impact on their family members in terms
of impact on your claim costs on your
plan
it is highly variable cancer is not one
thing it's
it's not a monolith it's highly
heterogeneous okay
the second reason you'd want to know
about this is oftentimes if you use a
stop-loss carrier
um or even if you don't use a stop-loss
carrier you would want to know if claims
are quote-unquote ongoing or not
and that's going to impact let's say
your stop-loss renewal
and that's where um the stop-loss
insurance be like look there's here's a
case of breast cancer that's ongoing
and because you watch this video you'll
be like yeah but it was dr carcinoma in
situ
and the woman has already undergone her
radiation and she had her surgery
so like that case is done so like it
doesn't really make clinical sense for
you to say to me
from a risk perspective that this is an
ongoing case
because it's not whereas if you had
somebody with maybe states through your
states for breast cancer
then it would likely be ongoing okay so
in terms of your future risk and it's an
implications for your stop-loss premium
specifically your stop your specific
stop-loss streams
then you would want to know about this
as well okay finally the last piece that
i would say to you is that
um sometimes employers that are sort of
more
advanced or forward-thinking if you will
they put into place a second opinion
program where they might travel to
a center of excellence for
cancer and it's important to note that
not all
cancers should go to a center of
excellence
one might argue that a basal cell
carcinoma there's no reason somebody to
get on a plane
for basal cell spiral zuma one might
argue that for different carcinoma in
situ one might not
get on a plane to go to a center of
accident because the treatment's fair
it's highly standardized okay how would
you determine which cancer is two or two
nuts
actually the center that you're
referring to so walmart uses mayo it
would be good to talk to that
center and be like okay what are those
what are the list
of cancers that would be good for you to
weigh in for a second opinion on
and what are ones that would
specifically not be good for you to
weigh in on
and then what are some of the ones that
are kind of in between and that would be
a very
um useful conversation to have if you
are considering
a cancer second opinion program so
that's my point on cancer today
thank you for watching healthcare see